Guide to the David Grant Noble Photographs of Southwestern Cultural Landscapes
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Photographs, 1971-2002; 80
  - Tyuonyi Pueblo and Cavates, Frijoles Canyon, New Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Noble: "Ancestors of present-day Tewa- and Keres-speaking Pueblo Indians inhabited Frijoles Canyon on the Pajarito Plateau between the late 1100s and mid 1500s. Tyuonyi, excavated in the early twentieth century, lies along Frijoles Creek, which flows out of the Jemez Mountains and into the Rio Grande. Many cavates were excavated into the volcanic tuff of the cliff above the pueblo. These rooms served as residences, kivas, and for storage. The area is under the protection of the National Park Service."
  - Moon House, Cedar Mesa, Utah, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Noble: "This cliff dwelling in southeastern Utah has been so well sheltered and little visited over the centuries that its mud and stone walls, wood-framed doorways, wood ceilings, and even paintings on plaster remain in fine condition. Cedar Mesa, which is transected by a series of canyons draining into the San Juan River, was a major area of habitation by Native Americans in the prehistoric period. It was abandoned in the late thirteenth century."
  - Paquimé, Chihuahua, Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Noble: "The prehistoric city known as Casas Grandes, or Paquimé, in northern Chihuahua, Mexico, became a major population and trade center between 1050 and 1450 with ties to the American Southwest. Charles C. Di Peso, who directed research at the site from 1958 to 1961, uncovered marketplaces with warehousing facilities, ceremonial mounds, ballcourts, plazas, and complexes of apartment buildings. Aviculture, especially the breeding of macaws, flourished here too. The city declined in the 1400s, and by the time Spaniards explored the valley, its once impressive buildings lay in ruins."
  - Basketmaker II Figures Along the San Juan River, Utah, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Noble: "These anthropomorphic petroglyph figures are characteristic of rock art made by early Basketmaker people prior to about 450, especially in southeastern Utah along the San Juan River. Typically, the bodies are large and broad-shouldered with seemingly ineffectual dangling appendages. The Basketmakers of this era depended heavily on hunting and gathering for their livelihood but also raised corn."
  - Holly Ruins, Hovenweep, Utah, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    See also: Cajon Group, Hovenweep, Utah, Box 3, folder 56
    See also: Holly Ruins, Hovenweep, Utah, Box 4, folder 77
    Noble: "The "Holly Unit" within Hovenweep National Monument is made up of residential architecture, towers, and the remains of a dam. Theories have abounded regarding the purpose and function of the towers, including from surveillance, signal towers, ritual, storage, and defense. They may have served all these uses at one time or another. Insights through archaeological research have been limited due to early looting and vandalism of the sites. Ancestral Pueblo culture flourished in the Hovenweep area between 1150 and the late 1200s."
  - Spanish Cavalcade, Canyon del Muerto, Arizona, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Noble: "A Navajo stronghold in the 18th and 19th centuries, Canyon de Chelly and Canyon del Muerto were periodically invaded by Spanish, Mexican and U.S. forces. A Navajo artist, it is believed, made this elaborate narrative painting above a high narrow ledge in the cliff above Standing Cow Ruin. It is thought to depict an historical event: a Spanish military expedition which entered the canyon in 1805. Note the soldiers' rifles and the cross on one rider's cape."
  - Monarch Cave, Butler Wash, Utah, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Noble: "The Monarch Cave cliff dwelling is one of hundreds of prehistoric sites in and around Butler Wash, a tributary of the San Juan River in southeastern Utah. The site is tucked under a protective alcove on the east side of Comb Ridge near a source of water. This region saw human settlement from Basketmaker II through Pueblo III times."
  - Dancing Figures, La Cienega, New Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Noble: "These petroglyphs of sprightly dancers are part of a larger panel located along an escarpment overlooking the lower Santa Fe River. Some researchers believe the panel relates a Pueblo myth. Executed in the Rio Grande Style, it probably dates to the same time period as nearby La Cienega Pueblo, which was inhabited until the Pueblo Revolt of 1680."
  - Katsina Being, Rinconada Canyon, New Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Noble: "The Katsina religion, which anthropologists think appeared in the Southwest in the early or mid-1300s, is frequently reflected in the iconography of rock art and kiva murals. Most commonly depicted are faces or masks. This example is part of an extensive concentration of petroglyphs along the seventeen-mile escarpment of Albuquerque's West Mesa. In 1990, the area was made a national monument."
  - Horned Serpent Petroglyph, Pueblo Blanco, Galisteo Basin, New Mexico, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Noble: "In the eastern Galisteo Basin of New Mexico, petroglyphs of the Horned Serpent often are depicted as a thick graceful snake form with forward-curving horn and dog-like snout. It is interpreted as representing the Pueblo deity Awanyu, guardian of springs and god of underworld water and has been traced in rock art far to the south. Polly Schaafsma, author of Rock Art of New Mexico, sees an analog in the Mexican Quetzalcoatl. This example is accompanied by a shield figure and face mask and dates to sometime between 1300 and 1700 CE."
  - Archaic Pictograph, Canyonlands, Utah, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Noble: "This armless painted goggle-eyed figure from the Archaic Period is part of the Bird Site in the Maze section of Canyonlands. The cliff surface was smoothed prior to applying the paint. Note that it has antennae, a feather, and an evergreen branch."
  - Mummy Cave, Canyon del Muerto, Arizona, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Noble: "Located about 12 miles up Canyon del Muerto from its junction with Canyon de Chelly, the Mummy Cave site has three components containing the remains of more than 80 ground-floor rooms in addition to numerous kivas and a well-preserved tower. Archaeological conclusions are that at least part of the pueblo was built in the 1280s by Anasazi immigrants from the Mesa Verde region. The presence of Basketmaker II pithouses indicates much earlier occupation, as well."
  - Petroglyph Panel, Petrified Forest, Arizona, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Noble: "Antelope are a ubiquitous theme in Southwestern rock art, the style varying from region to region. This herd or family appears on a boulder along the Puerco River in northeastern Arizona. The petroglyph panel probably is in close proximity to the Puerco Ruin, a 125-room pueblo which was founded in the mid-1200s."
  - Chaco Wash and Fajada Butte, Chaco Canyon, New Mexico, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Noble: "The intermittently flowing Chaco Wash flows west through Chaco Canyon, New Mexico, then turns north (becoming the Chaco River) finally to join the San Juan River. This view, looking east, also shows Fajada Butte, a prominent landmark in Chaco Canyon noted for the so-called Sun Dagger archaeoastronomical site on top."
  - Handprints and Human Figure, Grand Gulch, Utah, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Noble: "Grand Gulch, a tributary of the San Juan River in Southeastern Utah, contains uncounted archaeological and rock art sites that date from the Archaic Period through Pueblo III times. This pictograph panel is probably from the latter time period. Its meaning is not known."
  - Cavate and Ladder, Frijoles Canyon, New Mexico, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Noble: "Between around 1250 and 1550 CE, Pueblo people living in Frijoles Canyon and other canyons on the Pajarito Plateau in northern New Mexico carved rooms deep into the relatively soft volcanic tuff of the cliffs. These cavates, which were fronted by masonry architecture, were used for residential, storage, and ceremonial purposes. Frijoles Canyon alone contains more than a thousand cavate rooms."
  - Ute Petroglyph of a Horse, Bluff, Utah, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    See also: Archaic Pictographs, Horseshoe Canyon, Utah and Archaic Figures, The Maze, Utah, Box 1, folder 11
    Noble: "The Ute Indians once lived throughout what is now western Colorado and nearly all of Utah. By the mid-1600s, they had acquired captured horses from Spanish colonists in New Mexico and soon became expert horse breeders and riders. This petroglyph, pecked on a sandstone boulder, is one of numerous Ute rock art sites found along the San Juan River in southeastern Utah."
  - Kokopelli and Sun Petroglyphs, Comanche Gap, New Mexico, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Noble: "Comanche Gap, in the eastern Galiseo Basin of northern New Mexico, was a population center of Pueblo Indians between around 1300 and 1680. Many petroglyphs from this time period are concentrated along a volcanic dike that extends into the valley south of the present-day village of Galisteo. Depictions of flute players can be found throughout the Southwest and beyond."
  - Cliff Dwelling 1, Cedar Mesa, Utah, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    See also: A Cliff House, Cedar Mesa, Utah, Box 1, folder 20
    Noble: "Another part of the cliff house described in A Cliff House, Cedar Mesa, Utah ."
  - Petroglyph of Bird, Eastern Galisteo Basin, New Mexico, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Noble: "One of the most extensive collections of rock art in New Mexico is associated with the remains of San Cristobal Pueblo, located on a private ranch in New Mexico's eastern Galisteo Basin. San Cristobal Pueblo was inhabited by Tano Pueblo Indians until the outbreak of the Pueblo Revolt in 1680, when they occupied Santa Fe. Their descendants presently live on First Mesa, on the Hopi Reservation in Arizona. This bird form is one of thousands of examples of bird, animal, reptile, plant, and human figures."
  - Parrot and Cage, Boca Negra Canyon, New Mexico, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Noble: "West Mesa, on the west side of Albuquerque, New Mexico, contains another dense concentration of rock art, now under the protection of the National Park Service. This example, which shows a parrot and a cage, offers graphic evidence of the parrot trade that took place prehistorically between Mexico and the northern Southwest. The city of Paquimé, in Casas Grandes, Chihuahua was an important parrot raising and trading center."
  - Kiet Siel 1, Kiet Siel Canyon, Arizona, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Noble: "Kiet Siel is a well-preserved cliff dwelling in the Navajo Reservation (within the boundaries of Navajo National Monument) in northeastern Arizona. It consists of about 155 rooms and six kivas and was inhabited by Kayenta Anasazi people for a generation or two in the late 1200s. The site was first recorded by Richard Wetherill, a rancher from Mancos, Colorado, who took up exploring ancient Indian sites."
  - Archaic Rock Art Panel, Barrier Canyon, Utah, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    Noble: "This photograph shows a portion of the extensive Great Gallery site in Horseshoe Canyon (aka Barrier Canyon), Utah. The large figures are approximately human size. It is the type site for Barrier Canyon Style rock art, which is dated to the Archaic Period, which began as early as 5500 BCE. Although exposed to direct sun and rain, it is well preserved and free of vandalism. Later, small numbers of Anasazi farmers lived in this arid canyon region."
  - Snow Geese, Bosque del Apache, New Mexico, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    Noble: "For millennia, the Rio Grande Valley has been a source of sustenance for human beings as well as for animals and birds. Native Americans wove large nets with which to catch water fowl, especially during molting season. Today, many species of migratory birds – especially snow geese, sandhill cranes, and ducks – winter in the marshes of the Bosque del Apache, near present-day Socorro, New Mexico. Until soon after the arrival of Europeans in the region, Tiwa Pueblo Indians lived in the vicinity. Their economy included hunting, gathering plants, farming, and trading with their neighbors."
  - Cajon Group, Hovenweep, Utah, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    See also: Holly Ruins, Hovenweep, Utah, Box 2, folder 36
    Noble: "These architectural remains are part of the Cajon Unit within Hovenweep National Monument.
  - Star Petroglyph, Comanche Gap, Galisteo Basin, New Mexico, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    See also: Star Petroglyph, Comanche Gap, Galisteo Basin, New Mexico, Box 3, folder 59
    Noble: "Through long observation, Southwestern Indians acquired detailed knowledge of the heavens and attached mythical significance to celestial bodies. The movements of the sun and moon in relation to the horizon helped set calendars and determine when to hold religious ceremonies. Petroglyphs of four-pointed stars are common in the Galisteo Basin, some examples having faces, talons, and feathered headdresses. Some scholars think they represent Venus – the brightest planet and the morning and evening star – which holds special importance in Pueblo mythology and religion"
  - Betatakin, Arizona, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    See also: Betatakin Ruins, Northwestern Arizona, Box 1, folder 1
  - Star Petroglyph, Comanche Gap, Galisteo Basin, New Mexico, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    See also: Star Petroglyph, Comanche Gap, Galisteo Basin, New Mexico, Box 3, folder 57
  - Spruce Tree House, Mesa Verde, Colorado, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    See also: Spruce Tree House in Snowstorm, Mesa Verde, Colorado, Box 1, folder 7
  - Crack-in-Rock Pueblo, Arizona, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
    See also: Crack-in-Rock Pueblo, Arizona, Box 4, folder 68
    Noble: "Crack-in-Rock Pueblo lies northwest of Flagstaff in Wupatki National Monument. Its inhabitants were northern Sinagua Indians whose culture first appeared in the late seventh century on the eastern slopes of the San Francisco Mountains. Sometime around 1150, the Sinagua increased in population – immigration from the Kayenta region probably contributed to the growth – and they began building stonemasonry pueblos like Crack-in-Rock in and around the Wupatki Basin. The architecture of these monumental structures may well have been inspired by that of the ancestral Pueblo Indians (Anasazi) to the north and east."
  - Gathering Storm, El Guique, New Mexico, undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
    Noble: "An extensive collection of petroglyphs appears on basalt boulders on the west side of the Rio Grande along the base of Black Mesa. Today, descendants of the glyph makers live in the nearby Tewa pueblo of Ohkay Owingeh (formerly known as San Juan Pueblo) and Santa Clara Pueblo. This rock art probably dates to the late prehistoric period and into early historic times. The human-like figures are in Rio Grande Style of rock art, which is also reflected in pottery designs of the period."
  - Petroglyph of a Horned Serpent, Galisteo Basin, New Mexico, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
    Noble: "The horned serpent or Awanyu is a deity or mythological being in certain Pueblo traditions. In the Galisteo Basin it is often shown in large scale with an animal-like face, teeth, and a forward-bending horn. This example has a checkered neckband and dots on its body, which some researchers believe stand for corn kernels and raindrops. They also think the horned serpent may be a northern expression of Quetzalcoatl, the Plumed Serpent, who was an important Mesoamerican deity."
  - The Llano Estacado, New Mexico, undated (Box 4, Folder 64)
    Noble: "The Llano Estacado, or Staked Plains, of eastern New Mexico are a vast, dry region of the Southwest once the home of nomadic tribes including the Comanches and Pawnees. These peoples hunted bison and traded with (or raided) settlements and pueblos in Texas and New Mexico. Francisco Vásquez de Coronado's expedition crossed the Llano Estacado in 1541, while searching for fabled Quivira in what is now Kansas. Charles Goodnight and Oliver Loving drove cattle herds across the Llano during and after the Civil War. Today, much of the region remains empty or sparsely populated."
  - Wukoki Pueblo, Arizona, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    Noble: "Beginning in 1064, a series of eruptions on the east side of the San Francisco Peaks formed Sunset Crater and spread an estimated half-billion tons of volcanic cinders and ash over a wide region. A century later and continuing well into the 1200s, Sinagua Indians built Pueblo-style villages, including Wukoki, Wupatki, and Crack-in-Rock, in this harsh desert region. Their inhabitants stayed until the late 1200s and early 1300s, when they migrated south to found new settlements."
  - Tinaja, Pony Hill Site, New Mexico, undated (Box 4, Folder 66)
    See also: Footprint Trail Pony Hill Site, New Mexico, Box 2, folder 24
  - Stylized Lion Petroglyph. Three Rivers, New Mexico, undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
    See also: Bighorn Sheep, Three Rivers, New Mexico, Box 1, folder 19
  - Crack-in-Rock Pueblo, Arizona, undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
    See also: Crack-in-Rock Pueblo, Arizona, Box 4, folder 61
  - The Ghost Panel, Horseshoe Canyon, Utah, undated (Box 4, Folder 69)
    Archaic-period Indians painted these near life-size, ghostlike figures more than 1,500 years ago on the west side of the Colorado River in southeastern Utah. The panel, which remains in remarkably good condition after centuries of exposure to the elements, is an outstanding example of ancient shamanic art. It is part of a more extensive rock art collection known as the Great Gallery."
  - Painting of an Animal Face, Grand Gulch, Utah, undated (Box 4, Folder 70)
    Noble: "Images such as this painted visage of an animal, possibly a cougar, reflect a dark and fearful aspect of human consciousness. This one appears on a cliff in southeastern Utah's Grand Gulch, a tributary of the San Juan River and an area inhabited from Archaic through ancestral Pueblo times. The artist used reddish and white pigments – probably made from iron oxide and gypsum – to communicate a vision or dream, or perhaps a real-life experience."
  - Petroglyphs, Eastern Galisteo Basin, New Mexico, undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
    Noble: "The flute players, masks, and wavy lines shown here are common motifs in ancestral Pueblo rock art. Also faintly visible is an anthropomorphic figure with a diamond-shaped body and elaborate headdress. These examples are just a few among thousands found along the edge of a mesa on the privately owned San Cristobal ranch."
  - Cave Dwelling, Tsankawi, New Mexico, undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
    Noble: "Ancient eruptions in northern New Mexico's Jemez Mountains deposited layers of volcanic ash that compressed under its own weight to form tuff, a softer and more friable rock than the underlying basalt. Ancestral Tewa Pueblo people inhabited the cavates and pueblo on Tsankawi Mesa in the 15th and early 16th centuries. These sites today lie within the borders of Bandelier National Monument. "
  - Kiet Siel Cliff Dwelling, Kiet Siel Canyon, Arizona, undated (Box 4, Folder 73)
    Noble: "This village, with its 155 rooms and six kivas, perches on a ledge in a wide, deep cliff alcove in northeastern Arizona. The village overlooks a valley with a stream running through it. Ancestral Pueblo Indians lived here for a short time during the initial stages of their exodus from the Four Corners region. Dendrochronological studies of preserved roof timbers have dated the site to the 1260s and 1270s CE. Richard Wetherill, a rancher from Mancos, Colorado, first recorded Kiet Siel."
  - Archaic Figures, the Maze, Canyonlands, Utah, undated (Box 4, Folder 74)
    See also: Archaic Pictographs, Horseshoe Canyon, Utah and Archaic Figures, the Maze, Utah, Box 1, folder 11
  - Sunlit Mesa, Chama River Valley, New Mexico, undated (Box 4, Folder 75)
    Noble: "In the 1300s and 1400s thousands of ancestral Pueblo people lived in the southern Chama River Valley and along its tributaries in northern New Mexico. Farmers planted fields on the old river terraces, hunted in the nearby game-rich Jemez Mountains, and obtained high-quality chert from local stone quarries. By the early 1500s, however, they had left these villages and moved farther south to join Tewa Pueblo communities in the Rio Grande Valley."
  - Abstract Petroglyphs, Glorieta Mesa, New Mexico, undated (Box 4, Folder 76)
    Noble: "Much Archaic-period Southwestern rock art consists of abstract markings. These petroglyphs appear on a horizontal rock surface that was buried until uncovered by archaeologists. Dateable pieces of charcoal found in the overlying layers of soil allowed archaeologists to determine the art's early date."
  - Holly Ruins, Colorado, undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Detail of Petroglyph Panel, Sand Island, Utah, undated (Box 4, Folder 78)
    Noble: "One of the largest and most complex concentrations of petroglyphs in the Southwest is the Sand Island Site along the San Juan River in southeastern Utah. The panel includes figurative and abstract images dating from late Archaic times through the historic era. At the center of this photograph is a depiction of a flute player with long antennae, a slightly humped back, and an enlarged phallus. This iconic figure, also known as Kokopelli, appears in Southwestern rock art from the earliest Puebloan centuries."
  - White House and Chinle Wash, Canyon de Chelly, Arizona, undated (Box 4, Folder 79)
    Noble: "Well protected in a deep cliff crevice 35 feet above the floor of Canyon de Chelly, White House was the domicile of several ancestral Pueblo families from the late 1000s to late 1200s. The upper ruin visible in this photograph contains about 20 rooms. The mounds from a larger, multistory pueblo below it date to the same period. The architecture of White House suggests that it was an outlying Chacoan great house. Hopi Indians consider the site ancestral to their people and visit it periodically."
  - Waterfall, Cataract Creek Canyon, Arizona, undated (Box 4, Folder 80)
    Noble: "This watery landscape is on the Havasupai Indian reservation downstream of the village of Supai in the Grand Canyon. It is accessible only by foot or helicopter. Archaeologists think the Havasupais have lived in and farmed the canyon floor since between 1050 and 1200 CE."
    Cataract Creek Canyon is also known as Havasu Canyon.